UMAIR SUBHANI

Al-Khobar, 31952, Saudi Arabia Mobile: 00966-553048087 E-mail: umair112@hotmail.com

CAREER OBJECTIVE

To obtain a challenging position in a technical sale by adding value through utilizing my superior markets/products knowledge, selling abilities, management skills and experience in a progressive organization by effecting mutual employee and employer growth and success.

PROFILE

A qualified and experienced Techno-Commercial Business Executive with successful career of almost 16 years' in Sales and, Business Development of both industrial and speciality chemicals in a wide range of industries. Excellent track record of increasing market share, developing new products and achieving revenue and profit targets with a large organization in Saudi Arabia.

PROFESSIONAL CAREER

Rawabi Oil and Gas Co. (ROG)-Rawabi Holding Group Sales Engineer- Chemicals
Jan, 29th 2017-Present

Presently, working in a capacity of Sales Engineer for Industrial Chemicals.

Saleh & Abdul-Aziz Abahsain Co., Ltd; Khobar

Sep.2006 to Jan 2017

Senior Sales Executive – Industrial Chemicals (Commodities, Process & Specialities)

Abahsain is one of rapidly growing companies in Saudi Arabia and a major supplier of industrial and speciality chemicals to diversified industries including Paints & Coatings, Food & Beverages, Fiberglass, Plastic, Galvanizing, Paper & Ink, Adhesive, Personal Care, Glass & Detergents, Water Treatment, Power, and Oil and Gas, Petrochemicals etc.

• New Market and Product Development:

Utilizing new ideas, themes and diversification in the Chemicals industries and fulfilling the demand of local customers from international markets like speciality Solvents by developing new range of products.

"As a Sales Engineer, achieved continuous sales growth and annual revenues increased by 6%, 12%, 19%, 25% in the past four years.

Sales value increased during last four fiscal years as under:

2012-2013------ SAR 6-7.5 Million 2013-2014----- SAR 7.5-9 Million 2014-2015-----SAR 9-12 Million 2015-2016-----SAR12-14 Million

"Promoted new products from inception to commercialization such as,

ALKYD Resin

Copolymer /Homopolymer/Terpolymer (SABCRYL-P)

Gelcoats

Styreneted ALKYD

Solvents

Phosphates

Aluminum Tri-hydrate, Fiberglass Chop Strand Mats 450,300,600 GSM, Calcium Hypo 70%
Enzymes for Detergent Industry
Plasticizer
PVC Stabilizer
THF, Methyl Diethanolamine (nMDEA)
DMDS

- Strategic Working: Planning and executing new business ventures with Product Managers, Regional Manager, and Market Analysis by identifying and targeting specific areas of growth and retaining the clients with back-to-back orders and creating sales-forecast for the next 12 months.
- Short-Long Term Contract Negotiations: Negotiating the contractual business as per the objectives set by the management by careful cost-opportunity analysis.

"Awarded short and long-term contracts with key accounts including (name of the clients) SABIC, Saudi Chevron Colgate Palmolive, Procter & Gamble, Sigma paints, Hempel paints, Nalco, United Food Co., Coca Cola Co. Ltd., etc.

- Market Intelligence and Knowledge: Keeping abreast with in-depth market knowledge and identifying growth opportunities, competitors' activities, new projects and expansions, and key relevant factors to keep update the organization and the management to plan accordingly. Submitting timely and precise reports to senior managers.
- **Sales Team:** Continuous performance analysis to re-establish the sales strategies according to the market trends and developments to achieve sales targets.

Collections: Targeted collection plans, profitability report, monthly sales and gross-margin report, and sales/stock forecasting.

Co-ordination: Strong coordination with finance & procurement department for timely imports and clearing of shipments.

Specialised Sectors and Exclusive Assignments:

<u>Petrochemicals:</u> Solely managing the business of **BASF** Adsorbent and Catalyst product-range in Petrochemical manufacturers in Eastern region (Jubail)

<u>Fiberglass</u>: Exclusively developed the entire business of Abahsain Fibre-Glass Bahrain Plant's product-range in Fiberglass composites manufacturer in Dammam and Al Hassa.

"Achieved sale growth of Fiber-Glass business from zero to 75% from 2009-2016 and up to 3000 MT for Pipe, Liner ,profile, stationary tanks & reservoirs for water, solvents and chemicals.

Aramco: Responsible for Aramco drilling Chemicals and Glycols contracts business.

Responsible for day-to-day management of the accounts including initiating customer contact, making sales call, preparing quotations and follow up, inputting

sales orders and order confirmation to clients, arranging deliveries, processing sample requests, payment follow up and general problem solving. This includes market segments like Plastic & Rubbers, Paints, Coatings & Ink, Feed & Food, Detergent & Personal Care, Ceramics, Petrochemicals, Galvanizing, and Rigid & Flexible Plastics etc.

- Provide monthly/quarterly reports and sales forecast for all product lines.
- Meet internal reporting requirements and deadlines.
- Developed and maintained excellent customer relationships by meeting clients' needs.
 Established strong contacts and professional networking with customers and international chemicals suppliers operating in the market.
- Sound understanding of selling technical products and have worked with end-users, engineering companies and contractors.

Experience in Pakistan Chemical Industries:

Sales & Business Development Executive

MTC Trading Co, Karachi-Pakistan

(Exclusive Distributor of Huntsman's TIO2 in Pakistan)

Feb. 2003- Aug. 2006

Build-up **Titanium Dioxide** (Huntsman Brand) infrastructure in several fields like: Textile Printing, Artificial leather, Printing Inks, PVC -Plastic and Speciality Chemicals Mfg. Units etc. along with other Raw materials such as Carbon Black, Solvents, PVC Stabilizers, Chlorinated Paraffin wax etc.

New Business development through PRAL:

- ☐ **Consultation:** Making deals for the stock Chemicals of various fields & applications for trading business based on International price trend.
- ☐ **Research & Analysis:** R&D for the new product development for the local market.
- ☐ **Market Intelligence:** This includes in depth market & product knowledge, market size, market potential and various other factors which effects the initialization of an upcoming new product.

Sales Executive

Kay Chemical Pvt., Ltd. (Sole Agent of Degussa, Germany)

Feb. 2001 – Feb. 2003

- o Reporting to director marketing & Chief Executive.
- Technical Support & Services after sales to the customer.
- Co-ordinate with Technical & Commercial persons of parent companies during to professionally plan and manage their local visits and Products Promotional Seminars.
- Comprehensive knowledge of import procedure and documentation.
- Independently correspondence with suppliers and customers, with the help of team.
- Providing feed-back and market price for different products to parent companies.

Laboratory & Quality Control Supervisor

H.A. Rauf & Co. Karachi-Pakistan

Aug.1999- Jan. 2001)

Worked as an assistant Chemist & Supervisor in Lab for six months.

EDUCATION

- Bachelor's Degree in Chemical Technology/Engineering (University Of Karachi, 4 Years Bachelor's Degree) 1995-1999
- Intermediate Pre-Engineering from Govt. Delhi College, Karachi. 1992-1994

INDUSTRIAL TRAININGS:

- Six weeks training in Textile Division at "Clariant Scientific Research Centre Pakistan (Pvt.) Ltd., Karachi.
- Two weeks comprehensive training in Leather Processing at "National Institute of Leather Technology (NILT).

COMPUTER SKILLS & LANGUAGES

- Competent in Microsoft Office applications.
- Very good command of spoken/written English, and working knowledge of Arabic.

INDIVIDUAL SKILLS

- Excellent interpersonal, communication and negotiating skills.
- Able to communicate at all levels with good presentation skills & pleasant personality.
- Flexible & easy adaptable nature to adjust in diversified working environment.
- A team player with sparks of self-motivation and leadership qualities.
- Pro-active approach with good sense of observation, analysis & decision making.
- Problem solving, visualizing, planning & co-ordination with different departments.
- Cordial in building & maintaining business relationships within & outside organization.
- Focusing on the business & product development utilizing the cross functional business
- Strategies with in-depth research and analysis.
- In short, positive & serious approach towards work.
- Strong analytical skills and customer oriented style.
- Consultative approach and a natural team player.

PERSONAL INFORMATION

Nationality:

Date of Birth: 16th July 1975 Pakistani

• Flexible for relocation.

Marital status: Married and blessed with three children

References available on request.